To help us understand this phenomenon we'll take the help of an old friend,
为了方便我们理解这个情景 我们需要一位老朋友的帮忙
probability theory.
概率论
It gives us a formal mechanism to capture uncertainty in the real world.
概率论提供了一个正式机制来确定现实中的不确定性
And let's us make sensible decisions,
以便我们做出合理的决策
even when we are not fully sure about something.
哪怕我们对某些事情没有十足把握
&gt;&gt; Since the assignment of cars and
由于汽车和
goats is random, it doesn't really matter which one we pick first.
山羊是随机放置的 所以先选哪个并不重要
The chances that car is behind one of these doors
汽车会在某扇门后面的概率
is the same as the chances that is behind either of the other two.
和在另外两扇后的概率是一样的
&gt;&gt; We represent this by saying that the probability of the car being behind door
我们把汽车在 A 门后的概率记为
A, which we denote by P(CarA), is equal to P(CarB) and that is equal to P(CarC).
P(CarA) 因此 P(CarA) 和 P(CarB)、P(CarC) 都相等
Also, we know that one of these doors surely has the car behind it.
而且我们知道肯定有一扇门后放着汽车
And by convention,
通常
the probability of something that is certainly true is set equal to 1.
我们会将肯定为真的事件概率设为 1
Therefore, we can say that the sum of these probabilities equals 1.
因此 我们可以说这些概率加起来等于 1
&gt;&gt; From these two statements, we can conclude that
从上述两个说法中 我们可以总结出
each of these doors has a one-third probability of the car been behind it.
每扇门后有车的概率都为 1/3
This is known as prior probability.
这就叫先验概率
Which is essentially our best guess given no further evidence.
如果没有进一步的提示 这基本上就是我们猜对的最大概率了
Now let's say we now pick door A as our first choice.
现在 假设我们先挑了 A 门
&gt;&gt; Monty then opens one of the other two doors, say B,
于是 Monty 在另外两扇门中选一扇开出来 假设开了 B
to reveal a goat, which clearly implies that door B does not have the car.
露出了山羊 也就相当于说 B 门没有车
Here, open B is an observation we just made.
所以 打开 B 是我们刚做的一个观察
And the expression, P(CarB) | OpenB, is known as the posterior probability.
于是表达式 P(CarB | OpenB) (打开 B 门发现车子在其中的概率) 就是所谓的后验概率了
That is our belief after incorporating an observation, and
这也是结合了观察结果后我们得出的信念
in this case it is 0.
在本情景中 该概率为 0
Now, one way to think about this is that we have two doors left undisclosed.
现在 我们可以这么想 还有两扇门没打开
So the probability of the car being behind either one of them
所以每扇门后有车的概率
should be equal to half, right?
都应为 1/2 对吧？
&gt;&gt; Wrong, you glossed over the fact that Monty knowingly open the door with
错了 你忽略了一个事实 Monty 是在知道答案的前提下打开了
a goat behind it.
那扇有山羊的门的
He would never reveal the car at this stage.
他永远都不会在这个时候打开那扇有车的门
&gt;&gt; Ah-ha, so we are actually interested in finding out the posterior
啊哈 所以实际上我们要找的是 C 门后有车的后验概率
probability of the car being behind door C, given Monty opened door B and
由于 Monty 打开了 B 门
the implicit rule that he would never reveal the car.
而游戏规定他永远不会打开有车的门
&gt;&gt; Correct, we can express this posterior probability in terms of
对的 我们可以用其它数量关系来代表这个后验概率
other quantities that we can compute using Bayes' Theorem.
以便用贝叶斯定理来计算
Here, the first term, P(OpenB) | CarC, known as the likelihood, must be 1.
这里 第一项 P(OpenB | CarC) (车子在 C 门 打开 B 门的可能性) 也即所谓的似然性 肯定是 1
Because if the car is behind door C, Monty's only option is to open B,
因为如果汽车在 C 门后 Monty 就只能打开 B 门了
since we already picked A.
因为我们已经选了 A 门
The second term, P(CarC),
第二项 P(CarC)
is simply the prior, which we already computed to be one-third.
就是先验概率 而我们已经算出来 先验概率等于 1/3
&gt;&gt; And the last term, known as marginal probability,
最后一项为边缘概率
is a little tricky to compute.
有点难计算
There are three possibilities we have to consider.
我们需要考虑三个概率
The car could be behind door A which happens one-third of the time.
车子可能在 A 门后的概率是 1/3
And in this case, Monty could open either of B or C with equal probability.
这种情况下 Monty 可以开 B 也可以开 C 概率都一样
Therefore, P(OpenB) | CarA would be half.
因此 P(OpenB | CarA) (车子在 A 门 打开 B 门的可能性) 会是 1/2
Note that Monty cannot open door A as we've picked it as our first choice.
注意 Monty 不能开 A 门 因为我们一开始就选了这扇门
Or, the car could be behind door B,
或者 汽车可能在 B 门后
which also happens one-third of the time.
这概率也是 1/3
But in this case, Monty will certainly not reveal it,
但这个时候 Monty 肯定不会开 B 门
therefore P(OpenB) | CarB is 0.
因此 P(OpenB | CarB) (车子在 B 门 打开 B 门的可能性) 为 0
Finally, the car could be behind door C, also one-third of the time.
最后 汽车可能在 C 门 也是 1/3 的概率
In which case Monty is forced to open door B.
这种情况下 Monty 不得不打开 B 门
Hence, P(OpenB) | CarC is 1.
于是 P(OpenB | CarC) 为 1
&gt;&gt; Let's plug these values back into our Bayes' rule formulation.
现在我们把这些值代入贝叶斯定理公式中
As we can see, the probability that it is behind the other closed door
正如我们所见 车子在另一扇关闭的门里的概率
has increased to two-thirds.
增加到了 2/3
And even empirical evaluation indicates that a consistent switch strategy wins
就算是实证评估也表明另挑一扇门
two-thirds of the time.
能赢的概率有 2/3
&gt;&gt; It is fascinating how a careful characterization of a given situation,
这多有趣啊 为给定情景进行特征描述
combined with a formal method,
结合形式化方法
can help us make decisions even in the face of uncertainty.
就能帮我们作出决策 哪怕面对的是不确定性
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[空白音频]